<html>
<problem>
  
	<p>You drop a ball (initially at rest) from a height of 12 meters above the ground.  You can neglect air resistance.  Which statements are true about this situation?</p>

	<optionresponse texlayout="horizontal" max="10" randomize="yes" loncapaid="11">
		<p>The kinetic energy of the ball will be twice the gravitational potential energy when the ball is at a height of 2 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="OneA" correct="False" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The kinetic energy of the ball will be twice the gravitational potential energy when the ball is at a height of 4 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="OneB" correct="True" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The kinetic energy of the ball will be twice the gravitational potential energy when the ball is at a height of 6 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="OneC" correct="False" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The kinetic energy of the ball will be twice the gravitational potential energy when the ball is at a height of 8 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="" correct="False" options="('True','False')"/>
		
		<p>The kinetic energy and the gravitational potential energy of the ball are equal when the ball is at a height of 4 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="TwoA" correct="False" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The kinetic energy and the gravitational potential energy of the ball are equal when the ball is at a height of 6 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="TwoB" correct="True" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The kinetic energy and the gravitational potential energy of the ball are equal when the ball is at a height of 8 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="" correct="False" options="('True','False')"/>
		
		
		<p>The sum of KE + PE increases as the ball falls</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="ThreeA" correct="False" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The sum of KE + PE decreases as the ball falls</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="ThreeB" correct="False" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The sum of KE + PE stays the same as the ball falls</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="" correct="True" options="('True','False')"/>
		
		
		<p>The kinetic energy of the ball is 1/3 of the total energy when the ball is at a height of 2 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="FourA" correct="False" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The kinetic energy of the ball is 1/3 of the total energy when the ball is at a height of 4 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="FourB" correct="False" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The kinetic energy of the ball is 1/3 of the total energy when the ball is at a height of 6 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="" correct="False" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The kinetic energy of the ball is 1/3 of the total energy when the ball is at a height of 8 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="" correct="True" options="('True','False')"/>
		
		
		<p>The maximum value of gravitational potential energy occurs when the ball is at a height of 12 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="" correct="True" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The maximum value of kinetic energy occurs when the ball is at a height of 0 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="" correct="True" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The minimum value of gravitational potential energy occurs when the ball is at a height of 0 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="" correct="True" options="('True','False')"/>
		<p>The minimum value of kinetic energy occurs when the ball is at a height of 12 meters</p>
		<optioninput location="random" name="" correct="True" options="('True','False')"/>

	</optionresponse>
	
</problem>
</html>
