<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>
  <problem>
    <title>Video by Jonathan Abbot (MIT): Physics of Unicycling </title>
    <parameter default="2" description="Maximum Number of Tries" type="int_pos" name="maxtries" loncapaid="11">
      
        <p><table border="1"><tr><td><b>Physics Of Unicycling</b></td></tr><tr><td><iframe height="480" width="853" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/UzG9_8NgngI?rel=0"/></td></tr></table><br/>
As described in the video, the three forces primarily involved with unicycling are gravity, a normal force, and friction. In order to turn, a unicyclist (or a biker) may try a technique called countersteering. Which of the following offers a correct explanation for the process of by which a unicyclist can countersteer to make a turn?
</p>
      
      <br/>
      <multiplechoiceresponse max="10" randomize="no" loncapaid="12" type="MultipleChoice">
        <choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
          <choice location="1" name="foil1" correct="false">

                First steer towards the desired direction so that friction primarily acts towards the correct direction.
            
          </choice>
          <choice location="2" name="foil2" correct="true">

                First steer opposite the desired direction so that friction primarily acts radially inward.
            
          </choice>
          <choice location="3" name="foil3" correct="false">

                First steer towards the desired direction so that friction primarily acts radially inward.
            
          </choice>
          <choice location="4" name="foil4" correct="false">

                First steer opposite the desired direction so that friction primarily acts towards the correct direction.
            
          </choice>
        </choicegroup>
        <solved>
          
            <p>
Explanation: countersteering involves steering in the opposite direction to begin a turn. 
This causes the unicyclist to lean to the inside of the turn (radially inward).
Friction thus primary acts as a centripetal force, but this also causes a large torque about the center of mass. 
The leaning is necessary to make torque from the normal force partially offset the torque due to friction.
</p>
          
        </solved>
      </multiplechoiceresponse>
    </parameter>
  </problem>
</html>
