<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>
  <problem>
    <img width="400" encrypturl="no" src="/static/problems/MIT/RELATE/htmlwiki/Unit4/Module4/files/Accelvelpos.gif"/>
    <br/>
    
      <p>
By looking at the position versus time graph shown above, determine whether the position, the velocity and the acceleration are positive or negative at each of the eight numbered instants of time.  Also, determine whether the object whose position is plotted is speeding up ("accelerating") or slowing down ("decelerating") at each of these instants.  <br/>
<b>To answer:</b> Enter the sign of the position, velocity and acceleration and then "a" for accelerating or "d" for decelerating separated by commas.  For example, if the position is positive, the velocity is negative, the acceleration is positive and the object is decelerating you would enter <b>+,-,+,d</b>.<br/>
</p>
    
    <part loncapaid="1">
      
        <p><br/>Time 1:</p>
      
      <stringresponse answer="+,+,+,a" type="cs" loncapaid="11">
        <textline readonly="no" dojs="math"/>
        <hintgroup showoncorrect="no">
          
            <br/>
          
        </hintgroup>
      </stringresponse>
      <solution>
        
          <p>
            <br/>
            <i>
              <font color="green">Correct!  The position is positive since the graph is above the time axis.  The velocity is positive since the graph is moving upward.  The acceleration is positive since the slope is becoming steeper in the positive direction.  The object is "accelerating" rather than "decelerating" since the acceleration vector and the velocity vector are in the same direction (both positive).</font>
            </i>
</p>
        
      </solution>
    </part>
    <part loncapaid="2">
      
        <p><br/>Time 2:</p>
      
      <stringresponse answer="+,+,-,d" type="cs" loncapaid="12">
        <textline readonly="no" dojs="math"/>
        <hintgroup showoncorrect="no">
          
            <br/>
          
        </hintgroup>
      </stringresponse>
      <solution>
        
          <p>
            <br/>
            <i>
              <font color="green">Correct!  The position is positive since the graph is above the time axis.  The velocity is positive since the graph is moving upward.  The acceleration is negative since the slope is becoming less steep in the positive direction.  The object is decelerating since the acceleration vector and the velocity vector are in opposite directions (velocity positive, acceleration negative).</font>
            </i>
</p>
        
      </solution>
    </part>
    <part loncapaid="3">
      
        <p><br/>Time 3:</p>
      
      <stringresponse answer="+,-,-,a" type="cs" loncapaid="13">
        <textline readonly="no" dojs="math"/>
        <hintgroup showoncorrect="no">
          
            <br/>
          
        </hintgroup>
      </stringresponse>
      <solution>
        
          <p>
            <br/>
            <i>
              <font color="green">Correct!  The position is positive since the graph is above the time axis.  The velocity is negative since the graph is moving downward.  The acceleration is negative since the slope is becoming steeper in the negative direction.  The object is "accelerating" rather than "decelerating" since the acceleration vector and the velocity vector are in the same direction (both negative).</font>
            </i>
</p>
        
      </solution>
    </part>
    <part loncapaid="4">
      
        <p><br/>Time 4:</p>
      
      <stringresponse answer="+,-,+,d" type="cs" loncapaid="14">
        <textline readonly="no" dojs="math"/>
        <hintgroup showoncorrect="no">
          
            <br/>
          
        </hintgroup>
      </stringresponse>
      <solution>
        
          <p>
            <br/>
            <i>
              <font color="green">Correct!  The position is positive since the graph is above the time axis.  The velocity is negative since the graph is moving downward.  The acceleration is positive since the slope is becoming less steep in the negative direction.  The object is decelerating since the acceleration vector and the velocity vector are in opposite directions (velocity negative, acceleration positive).</font>
            </i>
</p>
        
      </solution>
    </part>
    <part loncapaid="5">
      
        <p><br/>Time 5:</p>
      
      <stringresponse answer="-,-,-,a" type="cs" loncapaid="15">
        <textline readonly="no" dojs="math"/>
        <hintgroup showoncorrect="no">
          
            <br/>
          
        </hintgroup>
      </stringresponse>
      <solution>
        
          <p>
            <br/>
            <i>
              <font color="green">Correct!  The position is negative since the graph is below the time axis.  The velocity is negative since the graph is moving downward.  The acceleration is negative since the slope is becoming steeper in the negative direction.  The object is "accelerating" rather than "decelerating" since the acceleration vector and the velocity vector are in the same direction (both negative).</font>
            </i>
</p>
        
      </solution>
    </part>
    <part loncapaid="6">
      
        <p><br/>Time 6:</p>
      
      <stringresponse answer="-,-,+,d" type="cs" loncapaid="16">
        <textline readonly="no" dojs="math"/>
        <hintgroup showoncorrect="no">
          
            <br/>
          
        </hintgroup>
      </stringresponse>
      <solution>
        
          <p>
            <br/>
            <i>
              <font color="green">Correct!  The position is negative since the graph is below the time axis.  The velocity is negative since the graph is moving downward.  The acceleration is positive since the slope is becoming less steep in the negative direction.  The object is decelerating since the acceleration vector and the velocity vector are in opposite directions (velocity negative, acceleration positive).</font>
            </i>
</p>
        
      </solution>
    </part>
    <part loncapaid="7">
      
        <p><br/>Time 7:</p>
      
      <stringresponse answer="-,+,+,a" type="cs" loncapaid="17">
        <textline readonly="no" dojs="math"/>
        <hintgroup showoncorrect="no">
          
            <br/>
          
        </hintgroup>
      </stringresponse>
      <solution>
        
          <p>
            <br/>
            <i>
              <font color="green">Correct!  The position is negative since the graph is below the time axis.  The velocity is positive since the graph is moving upward.  The acceleration is positive since the slope is becoming steeper in the positive direction.  The object is "accelerating" rather than "decelerating" since the acceleration vector and the velocity vector are in the same direction (both positive).</font>
            </i>
</p>
        
      </solution>
    </part>
    <part loncapaid="8">
      
        <p><br/>Time 8:</p>
      
      <stringresponse answer="-,+,-,d" type="cs" loncapaid="18">
        <textline readonly="no" dojs="math"/>
        <hintgroup showoncorrect="no">
          
            <br/>
          
        </hintgroup>
      </stringresponse>
      <solution>
        
          <p>
            <br/>
            <i>
              <font color="green">Correct!  The position is negative since the graph is below the time axis.  The velocity is positive since the graph is moving upward.  The acceleration is negative since the slope is becoming less steep in the positive direction.  The object is decelerating since the acceleration vector and the velocity vector are in opposite directions (velocity positive, acceleration negative).</font>
            </i>
</p>
        
      </solution>
    </part>
      </problem>
</html>
