<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>
<!-- two balls colliding vertically -->
<problem>

<script type = "loncapa/python">
from __future__ import division
import math
dt=0.001
M1 = random.randrange(720,1200,60)
M2 = M1/3
velocity = abs(3*M1-4*M2)/M2
impulse=(M1+M2)*9.8*dt
Pbefore=abs(2*M1-4*M2)
</script>

	<h2>Two balls colliding vertically</h2>

	<p>You first throw a ball of mass M<sub>1</sub> = $M1 kg vertically upwards. Immediately afterwards, you throw a second ball 
	of mass M<sub>2</sub> = $M2 kg (M<sub>2</sub> = M<sub>1</sub>/3), also vertically upwards. Just before the two balls collide, 
	the heavier ball is moving down with speed 2 m/s and the lighter ball is moving upwards with a speed of 4 m/s. Right after the 
	collision, the heavier ball is moving up with speed 1 m/sec. </p>

	<p>Find the velocity of the lighter ball right after the collision. Remember to start with clearly chosen co-ordinate system
	(mainly +/- directions).</p>
<p><b>Part a.</b> </p>

<p>The speed in m/s =</p>

      <numericalresponse answer="$velocity" unit="m/s">
        <responseparam default="5%" type="tolerance" name="tol" description="Numerical Tolerance"/>
        <textline/>
      </numericalresponse>

	<optionresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<p>
			<p>The direction of the velocity</p>
			<optioninput inline="1" options="('Up','Down')" correct="Down"/>
		</p>
	</optionresponse>
	
<p><b>Part b.</b></p>
<p>Consider the system to be both balls. Assuming that the collision takes place during a time interval of 1 ms (10<sup>-3</sup> s), 
calculate the magnitude of the impulse due to the gravitational force on the system during the time interval of the collision. Use 
g = 9.8 m/s<sup>2</sup> in your calculations.
</p>
 <p>The magnitude of the <b>External Impulse</b> in N.s =</p>

      <numericalresponse answer="$impulse" unit="m/s">
        <responseparam default="5%" type="tolerance" name="tol" description="Numerical Tolerance"/>
        <textline/>
      </numericalresponse>
	<br/>

<p><b>Part c.</b></p>
<p>Consider the system to be both balls. Calculate the magnitude of the momentum of the system at the instant right before 
the collision, P<sub>before</sub></p>
 <p><b>P<sub>before</sub></b> in N.s =</p>
      <numericalresponse answer="$Pbefore" unit="m/s">
        <responseparam default="5%" type="tolerance" name="tol" description="Numerical Tolerance"/>
        <textline/>
      </numericalresponse>
	<br/>
<p><b>Part d.</b></p>
<p>Compare the magnitude of the external impulse with the magnitude of the momentum of the system before the collision by doing
doing the ratio <b>(External Impulse)/(P<sub>before</sub>)</b>. What is this result useful for?
</p>
<ol>
<li>To show that the gravitational force always provides an external impulse to the system</li>
<li>I can justify the assumption that the linear momentum of the 2 balls system is constant during the collision as done in part a.</li>
<li>To estimate the impulse of the collision forces.</li>
</ol>
	<optionresponse direction="vertical" randomize="no">
		<p>
			
			<optioninput inline="1" options="('1','2','3')" correct="2"/>
		</p>
	</optionresponse>

</problem>
</html>

