<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>

<!-- MRI problem 12 -->

<problem>
	
	<p>A small block of mass m slides on a long horizontal table when it encounters a wedge of mass 2m and height h (see the diagram).</p>
	<img src="/static/problems/F12/MRI/images/MRI10.png" />
	<p>The wedge can also slide along the table. The mass slides up the wedge all the way to the top and then slides back down, never getting over the top. All surfaces are frictionless.</p>
	<p>Consider three moments in time: 
	<ul>
		<li>t1 – when the block is on the table, before sliding up the wedge; </li>
		<li>t2 – when the block is at the top of the wedge;</li>
		<li>t3 – when the block is on the table, after sliding down the wedge.</li>
	</ul>
	</p>

	<h3>Part 1</h3>
	<p>As the block is sliding up the wedge, what happens to the kinetic energy of the block; the potential energy of the block; 
	the mechanical energy of the block+Earth system; the kinetic energy of the wedge (respectively)?</p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice location="random" correct="true">decreases; increases; decreases; increases</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">decreases; increases; stays the same; increases</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">decreases; increases; stays the same; stays the same</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">increases; decreases; stays the same; stays the same</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

	<h3>Part 2</h3>
	<p>My answer to part 1 is justified because:</p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice location="random" correct="true">There is some transfer of the horizontal momentum of the block to the wedge.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">There is no friction between the wedge and the block.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">The wedge has a greater mass than the block.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">The increase in the potential energy of the block is equal to the decrease in the kinetic energy of the block.</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

</problem>

</html>