<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>

<!-- MRI problem 28 -->

<problem>
	
	<p>A brick of mass m slides down a frictionless slope of height h. You may treat the brick as a point object. At the bottom of the slope is a flat
	 patch with friction. </p>
	<img src="/static/problems/F12/MRI/images/MRI28.png" height="197" />
    
	<h3>Part 1</h3>
	<p>The goal is to determine the eventual speed of the brick after it has moved along the flat area for a given time \(t\). Consider the following approach for 
	determining the speed.</p>

<p>	<ol>
		<li>Use conservation of energy to determine the kinetic energy of the brick at the bottom of the slope.</li>
		<li>Use the mass of the brick to determine the normal force.</li>
		<li>Calculate the frictional force on the brick.</li>
		<li>Use the work-energy theorem to determine the change in kinetic energy over a particular distance, and thus the brick’s new kinetic energy.</li>
		<li>Use the new kinetic energy to determine the speed of the brick.</li>
	</ol>
	</p>
	<p>That solution has an error. At what step does this error appear? (Enter a number from 1 to 5).</p>

	<numericalresponse answer="4">
        <responseparam default="5%" type="tolerance" name="tol" description="Numerical Tolerance"/>
        <textline readonly="no" dojs="math"/>
	</numericalresponse>

	<h3>Part 2</h3>
	<p>How do you know that the error is there?</p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice location="random" correct="false">We are missing information that would be necessary for that step.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="true">We have not connected the distance traveled with the time elapsed.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">Energy lost to friction cannot be accounted for; we cannot use energy in this step.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">The effect of the curved slope cannot be accounted for.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">This is an energy problem; the use of force is inappropriate.</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

</problem>

</html>