<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>

<!-- MRI problem 2 -->

<problem>

	<p>An astronaut is holding onto a long aluminum antenna attached to a deep-space probe which is floating freely far from any other object. The astronaut is initially at rest, but then begins to climb out along the antenna.</p>

	<h3>Part 1</h3>
	<p>Which of the following statements accurately describes the linear momentum of the system containing the astronaut, antenna and space-probe during a time interval that starts when the astronaut is at rest and ends when the astronaut is in the process of climbing the antenna?</p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice location="random" correct="true">The linear momentum of the astronaut, antenna and space-probe system is conserved.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">The linear momentum of the astronaut, antenna and space-probe system is not conserved.</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

	<h3>Part 2</h3>
	<p>My answer to part 1 is justified because:</p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice location="random" correct="true">There are no external forces acting on the system.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">The astronaut’s work increased the system’s momentum.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">Linear momentum is always conserved.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">No friction is present.</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

	<h3>Part 3</h3>
	<p>Which of the following statements accurately describes the mechanical energy of the astronaut, antenna and space-probe system during a time interval that starts when the astronaut is at rest and ends when the astronaut is in the process of climbing the antenna?</p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice location="random" correct="false">The mechanical energy of the astronaut, antenna and space-probe system is conserved.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="true">The mechanical energy of the astronaut, antenna and space-probe system is not conserved.</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

	<h3>Part 4</h3>
	<p>My answer to part 3 is justified because:</p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice location="random" correct="false">There are no external forces acting on the system.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="true">The astronaut’s work increased the system’s mechanical energy.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">Mechanical energy is always conserved.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">No friction is present.</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

</problem>

</html>