<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>

<!-- MRI problem 30 -->

<problem>
	
	<p>You are a policeman investigating a car crash. Car #1 crashed into a stationary car #2. There is no indication that the driver of car #1 applied the 
	brakes before the collision. After the collision, the two cars stuck together and slid until they came to rest. </p>

	<h3>Part 1</h3>
	<br/>
	<p>Your goal is to determine whether car #1 was speeding before the collision. Consider the following steps for determining the speed of car #1.</p>
	<p>

	<ol>
		<li> Measure the length (d) of the skid marks for the cars to determine how far they slid after the crash.</li>
		<li> Look up the coefficient of kinetic friction ( \( \mu \) ) between the car tires and the ground.</li>
		<li> Look up the masses of the two cars (m<sub>1</sub>, m<sub>2</sub>).</li>
		<li> Find the amount of work done by friction as the cars slide, using the definition of work:
		 \( Work = \int{\vec{F} \cdot d\vec{x}} = -\mu \left( m_1 + m_2 \right) g d \).</li>
    	<li> Use conservation of energy to determine the speed of the cars just after the crash, \(v_f\), via the equation 
    	\( \frac{1}{2} ( m_1 + m_2) v_f^2 = \mu ( m_1 + m_2 ) g d \).</li>
		<li> Use conservation of energy to determine the initial velocity of the first car, \(v_1\), via the equation 
		\( \frac{1}{2} m_1 v_1^2  = \frac{1}{2} (m_1 + m_2) v_f^2 \).</li>
		<li> Compare \(v_1\) to the speed limit to see whether the car was speeding.</li>
	</ol>

	</p>
	<p>That solution has an error. At what step does this error appear? (Enter a number from 1 to 7). </p>

	<numericalresponse answer="6">
        <responseparam default="5%" type="tolerance" name="tol" description="Numerical Tolerance"/>
        <textline readonly="no" dojs="math"/>
	</numericalresponse>

    <br/>
	<h3>Part 2</h3>
	<p>How do you know that the error is there?</p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice location="random" correct="true">Since this is an inelastic collision, we cannot use conservation of mechanical energy during the collision.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">Since friction is involved, we cannot use conservation of mechanical energy.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">We have ignored the friction from before the cars crashed.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">The approach described is valid, but the equation listed in this step is incorrect.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">This step has too many unknowns or requires information that we do not have.</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

</problem>

</html>