<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>

<!-- MRI problem 6 -->

<problem>

	<p><i>This question presents a complex problem that may need to be broken into smaller sections in order to be solved. The diagram for the problem is broken into 7 arbitrary parts, or intervals. After the problem is presented, there will be several options for breaking the problem into manageable sub-problems. Choose the one answer that best describes how the problem should be divided.</i></p>
	
	<img src="/static/problems/F12/MRI/images/MRI6.png" />

	<h3>Part 1</h3>
	<p>A block of mass M is initially at rest on a spring of spring constant k that has been compressed a distance x from its equilibrium length. The spring is released, and shoots the block to a height h above the uncompressed position of the top of the spring. The goal of this problem is to determine the height h in terms of the other quantities and gravity. What is the most appropriate way to decompose the problem? </p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice location="random" correct="true">a. One problem: intervals 1-5</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">b. Two sub-problems: intervals 1-2 and 2-5</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">c. Three sub-problems: intervals 1-2, 2, and 2-5</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">d. Three sub-problems: intervals 1-2, 2-5, and 5</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

	<h3>Part 2</h3>
	<p>My answer to part 1 is justified because:</p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice location="random" correct="true">a. Mechanical energy is conserved throughout.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">b. It is necessary to find the speed of the block as it leaves the spring.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">c. The forces change when the block leaves the spring.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">d. The acceleration drops to zero at the top.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">e. Statements b, c and d are all needed to explain the decomposition.</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

</problem>

</html>