<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>
<!--An asteroid and a star-->
<problem>

<h3>Solution</h3>

<p>System : asteroid, the only force on it is the gravitational force due to the star.</p>
<img src="/static/problems/S13/solutions/images/7-1.png" />
<img src="/static/problems/S13/solutions/images/7-1(2).png" />

<p>In the figure above (not in scale):</p>
<p>\(\vec{ds}\): is the element of the displacement along the asteroid’s path between points A and B.</p>
<p>\(\vec{F}_{G}\) = - \({GmM\over r^{2}} \hat{r}\) is the gravitational force exerted on the asteroid by the star.</p>
<p>r =|\(\vec{r}\)| is the distance between the star and the asteroid.</p>
<p>\(\hat{r}\) is the unit vector along the line joining the star and the asteroid and \(\hat{\theta}\) is the unit vector
perpendicular to \(\hat{r}\). Note that \(\hat{\theta}\) is not necessarily tangent to the orbot because the path is
not a circle. As a result the element of displacement \(\vec{ds}\) has two components along the polar coordinate system: \(\vec{ds}\) = dr\(\hat{r}\) + ds<sub>\(\theta\)</sub>\(\hat{\theta}\) (where ds<sub>\(\theta\)</sub> = rd\(\theta\). Therefore, the dot product between the gravitational force and \(\vec{ds}\) becomes:</p>
<p>\(\vec{F}_{G}\) \(\vec{ds}\) = \({-GmM\over r^{2}} \hat{r} *dr \hat{r}\) + ds<sub>\(\theta\)</sub> \(\hat{\theta} =  {-GmM\over r^{2}}\) dr</p>
<p>We now calculate the work done by the gravitational force on the asteroid to move from
point A to point B:</p>
<p>\(\displaystyle W_{AB} = \int_{\vec{r}_{A}}^{\vec{r}_{B}} \! \vec{F}_{G} \, \mathrm{d}\vec{s}\) =  \(\int_{\vec{r}_{B}}^{\vec{r}_{A}} \! {-GmM\over r^{2}} \, \mathrm{d}r\) = \({GMm\over r}\)]<sub>\(\vec{r}\)<sub>A</sub></sub><sup>\(\vec{r}\)<sub>B</sub></sup> = GMm(\({1\over r_{B}} - {1\over r_{A}}\))</p>
<p>where r<sub>A</sub> = |r<sub>A</sub>| amd r<sub>B</sub> = |r<sub>B</sub>| are the distances between the star and the asteroid at points A and B</p>
<p>The work done by the gravitational force on the asteroid is given by:</p>
<p>W<sub>AB</sub> = GMm(\({1\over r_{B}}\) - \({1\over r_{A}}\))     (eq.1)</p>
<p>Note that the work is positive (W<sub>AB</sub>> 0) if r<sub>A</sub> > r<sub>B</sub>, the asteroid is getting closer to the star, and it is negative (W<sub>AB</sub>0) if r<sub>A</sub> &#60; r<sub>B</sub> , the asteroid is moving away from the star.</p>
<p>ii) Consider the system to be the asteroid, the only force acting on it is external(gravitational), then the work kinetic energy theorem applied to the asteroid implies:</p>
<p>K<sub>B</sub> = K<sub>A</sub> + W<sub>AB</sub><sup>external</sup> \(\Rightarrow\) K<sub>B</sub> - K<sub>A</sub> = GMm(\({1\over r_{B}}\) - \({1\over r_{A}}\))</p>
<p>If r<sub>A</sub> > r<sub>B</sub> then W<sub>AB</sub> > 0, the kinetic energy increases and the asteroid moves faster when
approaches the star</p>
<p>If r<sub>A</sub> &#60; r<sub>B</sub> then W<sub>AB</sub> &#60; 0, the kinetic energy decreases and the asteroid moves slower when
moves away from the star.</p>
<p>The kinetic energy of the asteroid changes because of the work done by the gravitational
force on the asteroid</p>
<p>b) System: Asteroid+Star.</p>
<p>i) Interactions: there is only one internal interaction between the star and the asteroid.
Because it is conservative then its work is represented by the gravitational potential
energy. (No external interactions).</p>
<p>Use the mechanical energy and work principle:</p>
<p>E<sub>B</sub> = E<sub>A</sub> + W<sub>AB</sub><sup>ext</sup> + W<sub>AB</sub><sup>internal, NC</sup>, for the asteroid star system there is only an internal and conservative interaction, therefore both works are zero and the mechanical energy is constant between points A and B.</p>
<p>E<sub>B</sub> = E<sub>A</sub> + W<sub>AB</sub><sup>ext</sup> + W<sub>AB</sub><sup>internal, NC</sup> \(\Rightarrow\)</p>
<p>E<sub>B</sub> = E<sub>A</sub> \(\Rightarrow\)</p>
<p>K<sub>B</sub> + U<sub>B</sub> = K<sub>A</sub> + U<sub>A</sub> \(\Rightarrow\)</p>
<p>K<sub>B</sub> - K<sub>A</sub> = -(U<sub>B</sub> - U<sub>A</sub>) = W<sub>AB</sub> \(\Rightarrow\)</p>
<p>Using eq. 1 in the expression above:</p>
<p>K<sub>B</sub> - K<sub>A</sub> = GMm(\({1\over r_{B}} - {1\over r_{A}}\))</p>
<p>Using eq. 1 in the expression above:</p>
<p>Assumptions:</p>
<p>1. Infinite massive object assumptions: M >> m, therefore there is no change of
kinetic energy of the star while the asteroid is interacting with it.</p>
<p>2. Only the interaction between the asteroid and the star is considered. We neglect all
possible interactions with other celestial objects.</p>
<p>Another way to calculate the work is to use the fact that the gravitational force is
conservative therefore its work is independent of the path. Then, instead of moving along
the orbit to go from point A to point B we can choose another path easier to do the
integral.</p>
<p>Consider two circles. One circle of radius r<sub>A</sub>, passing through point A, and another circle of radius r<sub>B</sub>, passing through point B, as shown. The center of each circle coincides with the star. Instead of moving along the orbit to go from point A to point B we can move along the line joining point A and the star, from point A to point C, and then move along the circle of radius rB, from points C to point B.</p>
<p>\(\displaystyle W_{AB} = W_{AC} + W_{CB} = \int_{A}^{C} \! \vec{F}_{G} \, \mathrm{d}\vec{s} + \int_{C}^{B} \! \vec{F}_{G} \, \mathrm{d}\vec{s}\)</p>
<p>The integral along the circle of radius r<sub>B</sub> is zero because \(\vec{F}_{G}\) \(\bot\) d\(\vec{s}\)</p>
<p>To evaluate \(\int_{A}^{C} \! \vec{F}_{G} \, \mathrm{d}\vec{s} = \int_{C}^{B} \! \vec{F}_{G} \, \mathrm{d} \hat{r}\), which is the integral we have already solved in the first part.</p>

</problem>
</html>
