<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>
  <problem>
    <script type="loncapa/python">
from __future__ import division
from loncapa import *

#Enter the computations here
t=11.664

	</script>
    
	<p>You are participating in an unusual drag race. You start from rest and try to cover a straight quarter-mile (400 meters, for the purpose of this problem) in the shortest time possible. Your car is very well built so it can achieve speeds of up to 360 km/h. It is equipped with a very powerful engine and an excellent anti-lock braking system. The coefficient of static friction between the wheels and the road is about 1.2 (the drag-race tires are made of very soft rubber which is pre-heated before the start by spinning the wheels; as a result, the wheels achieve the effective coefficient of friction greater than 1). </p>
	<p>However, there is a crucial difference: you are required, for publicity purposes, to come to a dead stop at the finish line (in a typical drag race, you would fly right through that finish line!).</p>

<part loncapaid="11"><br/>What is the best strategy for finishing the race in the shortest time possible while coming to a stop at the finish line?

<optionresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
    <p>speed up at the maximum possible rate for the first half of the distance; then slow down at the same rate
    <optioninput name="Foil1" options="('True','False')" correct="True"></optioninput></p>
    <p>speed up at a constant rate until you achieve the maximum possible speed; then slow down
    <optioninput name="Foil2" options="('True','False')" correct="False"></optioninput></p>
    <p>speed up at a constant rate until you achieve the one/half of the maximum possible speed; then slow down
    <optioninput name="Foil3" options="('True','False')" correct="False"></optioninput></p>
    <p>speed up at one-half the maximum possible rate for the first half of the distance; then slow down at the same rate
    <optioninput name="Foil4" options="('True','False')" correct="False"></optioninput></p>
</optionresponse>

</part>

<br/>

<part loncapaid="13">
<p>What is the shortest possible time needed to complete the race (in seconds)?</p>
<p>\(t=\)</p>
<numericalresponse answer="$t" loncapaid="14">
	<responseparam default="3%" type="tolerance" name="tol" description="Numerical Tolerance"/>
	<textline dojs="math"/>
</numericalresponse>
</part>

  </problem>
</html>
