<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>
  <problem>
    <parameter default="2" description="Maximum Number of Tries" type="int_pos" name="maxtries" loncapaid="11">
      <img src="/static/problems/MIT/boriskor/BKimages/Stacked blocks_bottom_pull.png" alt="Two stacked blocks on a table; bottom block pulled horizontally" encrypturl="no"/>
      <br/>
      
        <p>
Two blocks of equal masses are placed on a horizontal table as shown. The bottom block is then pulled with a slowly increasing horizontal force \(F\). 
The coefficients of static friction for both surfaces are greater than zero and equal to each other.<br/>
Select the correct description of the motion of the blocks. <b>Note: "move" or "does not move" refers to the laboratory ("Earth") frame of reference.</b>
</p>
      
      <br/>
      <multiplechoiceresponse max="10" direction="vertical" randomize="yes" loncapaid="12" type="MultipleChoice">
        <choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
          <choice location="random" name="foil1" correct="false">

                The top block begins to move as soon as F reaches a certain minimum value; the bottom block would never move even as F increases further.
          </choice>
          <choice location="random" name="foil2" correct="false">

                The top block begins to move as soon as F reaches a certain minimum value; the bottom block does not move at that instant but would begin to move as F increases further.
            
          </choice>
          <choice location="random" name="foil3" correct="true">

                Both blocks begin to move simultaneously as F reaches a certain minimum value; as F increases further, the acceleration of the bottom block exceeds the acceleration of the top block.
            
          </choice>
          <choice location="random" name="foil4" correct="false">

                The bottom block begins to move as soon as F reaches a certain minimum value; the top block would never move even as F increases further.
            
          </choice>
          <choice location="random" name="foil5" correct="false">

                The bottom block begins to move as soon as F reaches a certain minimum value; the top block does not move at that instant but would begin to move as F increases further.
            
          </choice>
          <choice location="random" name="foil6" correct="false">

                Both blocks begin to move simultaneously as F reaches a certain minimum value; as F increases further, both blocks always have the same acceleration.
            
          </choice>
          <choice location="random" name="foil7" correct="false">

Both blocks begin to move simultaneously as F reaches a certain minimum value; as F increases further, the acceleration of the top block exceeds the acceleration of the bottom block.
          </choice>
        </choicegroup>
      </multiplechoiceresponse>
      
    </parameter>
  </problem>
</html>
