<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>
  <problem>
    <script type="loncapa/python">
from __future__ import division
from loncapa import *

a= "(m*v^2)/L-m*g*sin(theta)"
b= "arcsin(v^2/(L*g))"
c= "sqrt(L*g)"

</script>

<img encrypturl="no" src="/static/problems/MIT/rayyan/problemset/Pictures/p2.PNG" alt="p1a" texwrap="none" align="top"/>
    
<p>A u-control airplane of mass M is attached by control wires of length L and negligible 
mass to the "pilot" who controls the lift provided by the wing \(F_L\). The wires control 
the plane's elevator or angle of attack. The plane's engine keeps it moving at constant 
speed v in a horizontal circle.
</p>

a) Find the magnitude of the force of tension T in the wires when the plane is flying in a circle at an 
altitude such that the wires make an angle \(\theta\) with the ground. Remember that the wings 
can provide lift only in the direction <b>perpendicular</b> to their area, i.e. in a direction 
perpendicular to the wires. Think carefully before selecting the angle of your 
coordinate system. 
Use variables m, v, L, theta, and g in your answer. 
    <br/>
    <part loncapaid="9">
      <formularesponse answer="$a" samples="g,theta,m,v,L@1,1,1,1,1:10,10,10,10,10#4" loncapaid="10">
        <textline readonly="no" size="25" dojs="math"/>
      </formularesponse>
    </part>
    <br/>
    
      <p>
b) The plane will go out of control and crash if the tension is not maintained in the 
control wires. Given a particular speed of the plane, v, what is the angle \(\theta\) at which 
you would advise the pilot not to exceed? (For inverse trig function, use "asin" for arcsin, "acos" 
for arccos, and "atan" for arctan.) Use the variables v, L, and g, in your answer. <br/>
</p>
    
    <part loncapaid="11">
      <formularesponse answer="$b" samples="v,L,g@.1,1,1:.9,10,10#4" loncapaid="12">
        <textline readonly="no" size="25" dojs="math"/>
      </formularesponse>
    </part>
    <br/>
    
      <p>
c) Is there a minimum speed, v_safe, at which the plane would be safe at any angle? If not, 
explain why not. If yes, find v_safe. Use L and g in your answer.
</p>
    
    <part loncapaid="15">
      <formularesponse answer="$c" samples="L,g@1,1:10,10#3" loncapaid="16">
        <textline readonly="no" size="25" dojs="math"/>
      </formularesponse>
    </part>
    <br/>
              </problem>
</html>
