<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>
  <problem>
    <img src="/static/problems/MIT/rayyan/Physics801/Figures/Spinning_rod_v4.png"/>
    <script type="loncapa/python">
from __future__ import division
from loncapa import *

</script>
    <hr/>
    
      <p>
      A long narrow uniform stick of length D and mass M lies motionless on a smooth icy surface contained in the (x,y) plane. The moment of inertia of the stick about 
      its center of mass is \(I_{cm}\). A puck of mass m  slides without spinning on the ice with a speed of v<sub>i</sub> toward the stick. After hitting
       one end of the stick the puck moves with speed v<sub>f</sub> without changing direction as shown in the picture. The radius of the puck is 
       much smaller than the length of the stick. (Gravity is into the screen).
</p>

<b>Part a:</b><br/>
<p>
Which of the following statements about the <i>puck-stick system</i> are true or false?
</p>
<p>
1st Statement: The linear momentum of the system is constant.
</p>

<optionresponse>
      <optioninput options="('true','false')" correct="true"/>
    </optionresponse>

<p>
2nd Statement: The angular momentum with respect to any given point is constant.
</p>

<optionresponse>
      <optioninput options="('true','false')" correct="true"/>
    </optionresponse>

<p>
3rd Statement: The angular momentum is constant only with respect to the stick-puck’s center of mass.
</p>
<optionresponse>
      <optioninput options="('true','false')" correct="false"/>
    </optionresponse>

<b>Part b:</b><br/>
What is \(v_{s}\), the speed of the center of mass of the stick, after the collision? 
<br/>
\(v_s=\)    
    <br/>
    <formularesponse answer="m*(vi-vf)/M"  samples="vi,vf,m,M@1,1,1,1:30,30,30,30#4" loncapaid="1">
      <responseparam default="0.00001" type="tolerance" name="tol" description="Numerical Tolerance"/>
      <textline readonly="no" size="25" dojs="math"/>
    </formularesponse>

<b>Part c:</b><br/>
If the moment of inertia of the stick about its center of mass is I<sub>cm</sub> =MD<sup>2</sup>/12, what is the angular velocity of the stick after the collision? 
Enter your answer in terms of some or all of the variables m, M, vi, vf and D.
<br/>
\(\omega=\)    
    <br/>
    <formularesponse answer="6*m*(vi-vf)/(D*M)"  samples="vi,vf,m,M,D@1,1,1,1,1:30,30,30,30,30#4" loncapaid="1">
      <responseparam default="0.00001" type="tolerance" name="tol" description="Numerical Tolerance"/>
      <textline readonly="no" size="25" dojs="math"/>
    </formularesponse>

  </problem>
</html>
