<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html>

<!-- Colin problem #5 -->
<!-- Also an MRI problem -->

<problem>
	<h3>Part 1</h3>
	<p>You are building a missile defense system to shoot down ICBMs, nuclear missiles, that are fired on elliptical trajectories that can take them 
	anywhere on Earth. To simplify the problem, you may assume that the missiles do not burn fuel after they leave the atmosphere.</p>
	<p>It will be easiest to hit the missiles when they are moving slowly. When in their trajectory should you try to hit them?</p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="no">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice correct="false">Just after the missiles leave the atmosphere.</choice>
			<choice correct="true">At the missiles' farthest distance from the Earth.</choice>
			<choice correct="false">Just before the missiles return to Earth.</choice>
			<choice correct="false">Some other time.</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

	<h3>Part 2</h3>
	<p>Why did you choose this answer?</p>
	<multiplechoiceresponse direction="vertical" randomize="yes">
		<choicegroup type="MultipleChoice">
			<choice location="random" correct="false">At this point, atmospheric drag will have slowed the missile down.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">The acceleration from Earth's gravity will be the smallest here, so the rocket's speed will also be 
			the smallest.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="true">Kepler's Second Law indicates that the missile's speed will be smallest here.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">Newton's Third Law says that the missile and Earth put the same force on each other, which is 
			smallest here.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">Kepler's Third Law relates the time the missile takes to its distance from Earth. The farther 
			up the missile is along its path, the more time it takes.</choice>
			<choice location="random" correct="false">At this distance gravity from the Moon will also be pulling on the missile, slowing it down.</choice>
		</choicegroup>
	</multiplechoiceresponse>

</problem>
</html>